拿撒勒人散播谣言说
The Nazarene spread rumor that he would rise
他会在死去三天后复生
from his own death after three days.
让神殿的护卫把守在外面
Post temple guards outside.
而我会派遣罗马士兵
And I will post Roman soldiers.
- 我看到他了  - 谁?
- I saw him.  - Who?
耶稣
Jesus.
你相信他已经死而复生了吗?
Do you believe he has risen from the dead?
他曾保证这些都会发生
It's what he promised would happen.
是时候由我们来结束这个故事了
It's time we shut this story down.
杀掉所有坟墓守卫
Kill all the tomb guards.
罗马皇帝的封印已经被破坏了
The Emperor's seal is broken.
我们究竟是走还是留?
Do we stay or go?
我让我的朋友们去城门口集合
I told my friends to make their way to the city gate
- 然后想办法找到一条路  - 我们可以帮忙
- so we can find a way out.  - We can help.
- 现在就走  - 你为什么帮助我们?
- Go now.  - Why are you helping us?
罗马人的敌人就是我们的朋友
An enemy of theirs is a friend of ours.
是看守拿撒勒人坟墓的祭司们
The priests guarding the Nazarene's tomb.
他们怎么了?
What of them?
其中两位发现被人谋杀 而其余的都失踪了
Two of them found murdered, and the others are missing.
回到耶路撒冷等待即可
Go back to Jerusalem and wait.
圣灵降临在你们身上 你们就必得着能力
And the power of the holy spirit will come to you.
本片涉及圣经内容的名词 段落 均参照和合本翻译
公元: 圣经续 第一季第3集
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调: 影子
翻译: 猫呗 舒舒 飘飘行天下
翻译: 鸟生鱼汤 波特妹子
校对: 飘飘行天下 影子
加利利
我要怎么和我的女儿说我不能留下?
How do I tell my daughter I can't stay, hmm?
我怎么能和我的孩子说爱她 然后就离开?
How can I tell my child I love her and then leave?
她和祖母在这更安全
She's safer here with her grandmother.
耶路撒冷是个危险之地
Jerusalem is a dangerous place.
彼得...
Peter...
我们得回城去了
We have to go back to the city
然后等待圣灵降临
and wait for the holy spirit.
她开始长得像她的母亲了
She's starting to look like her mother.
愿神安息她的灵魂
God rest her soul.
父啊 照顾好我的孩子
Father, take care of my child.
阿门
Amen.
我们去看看耶路撒冷究竟有什么等着我们
Let's see what Jerusalem holds for us.
走吧 约翰
Come, John.
但愿一切已经平息下来了
Let's hope things have calmed down now.
耶路撒冷
我的丈夫被谋杀了!
My husband has been murdered!
我和三个孩子被孤苦伶仃地留在这世上
And I'm left alone in the world with three children.
你丈夫是深受信赖的神殿守卫
You have the sympathy of all at the temple
神殿所有同仁爱他 也向你表示深切哀悼
who worked with and loved a most trusted temple guard.
他的同仁多数也被谋杀了
Most of those whom he worked with have been killed, too.
你让他们看守那个拿撒勒人的墓地 对吗?
You had them guard the Nazarene's tomb?
我们将不遗余力
We'll leave no stone unturned
去搜寻谋杀犯... 相信我
in pursuit of their murderers... trust me.
我们会送一些神殿里的救济食物和礼品
Charitable food and gifts from the temple
到你家中
will be delivered to your home.
你听到了?
You heard?
她起疑心了
She suspects.
她刚新丧
She's in mourning.
她在寻找理由 仅此而已
She's looking for reasons. That's all.
六个人... 六个祭司被我们的罗马大人残杀!
Six men... six priests murdered by our Roman master!
你知道为什么彼拉多要这么做
You know why Pilate did this.
他必须清除当晚所有证人...
He had to remove all witnesses to that night...
才能让那个荒唐的复活故事
to ensure that the ridiculous story of the resurrection
在愚民面前丝毫立不住脚跟
garners no credence amongst the gullible.
它和那些士兵还有神殿守卫一起被埋葬了
It dies along with the soldiers and the temple guards,
本该如此
as it should.
他们的死亡是必要的牺牲
Their deaths are a necessary sacrifice.
但是那些家属...
But the families...
我们会留意确保他们得到照顾
We'll see to it that they're looked after.
快喝完 我们要打烊了
Drink up. We must close now.
过来 过来
Come, come.
我们得去把房间收拾出来
We need to get the rooms ready.
街上人都满了
The streets are filling.
不像我的杯子 依旧空空如也
Unlike my cup, which remains resolutely empty.
马库斯·德鲁苏斯 你每个斋戒日都这样
Marcus Drusus, you do this every feast day.
你是个好人 埃里克
You're a good man, Arik...
你是个糟糕的掌柜 但是个好人
A lousy landlord, but a good man.
站起来 快点 快点
On your feet. Come on, come on.
快点!
Come on!
原谅我 朋友 不小心
Forgive me, friend. Clumsy.
不要伤人
No harm done.
刚刚是个意外
It was an accident.
波阿斯?
Boaz?
- 跟我走  - 不要伤人
- Follow me.  - No harm done.
波阿斯!
Boaz!
还不到时候!
Not yet!
那个拿撒勒人的随从可能会利用这个时机
The Nazarene's men might use this moment
挑起更多骚动
to stir up more trouble.
继续在街上巡逻
Keep patrolling the streets,
至少巡逻到斋戒日结束
at least until the festival is over.
这里发生了什么事?
What happened in here?
政治问题 没什么的
Politics. Nothing more.
我和你在一起已久
I've been with you long enough
你有什么困扰我能看出来
to know when something's troubling you.
我没有困扰
I'm not troubled.
别把我和别人的妻子混为一谈
Don't confuse me with other people's wives.
我怎么会呢?
How could I?
你若以诚待我 我便会伴你左右
If you deal honestly with me, I'll stand beside you.
- 克劳迪娅...  - 究竟发生了什么事?
- Claudia...  - What happened?
确实有件小事让我困扰了一段时日
I was troubled for a time by a minor irritation.
结果你就
Which you dealt with
杀掉那些看守拿撒勒人坟墓的人?
by having the Nazarene's tomb guards killed?
就在这 在我屋子里?
Here, in my house?
我们不应该对彼此有所隐瞒
We shouldn't keep secrets from each other.
确实不该
No, we shouldn't.
今天又是新的一天
Today is a new day,
希律同他的妻子要来拜访
with a visit from Herod and his wife.
让我们一起迎接他们
Let's welcome them together.
让开! 给希律·安提帕王让路!
Make way! Make way for King Herod Antipas!
希律王!
The King!
给希律王让路!
Make way for King Herod Antipas!
希罗底 是我一个人这么觉得
Herodias, is it me,
还是拿撒勒人耶稣被钉死之后
but since the crucifixion of the Nazarene,
街上的罗马士兵确实比平常多了?
are there more Roman soldiers in the streets than usual?
街上的士兵确实更多了 没错
There's definitely more soldiers, yes.
守卫!
Guard!
这是什么意思?!
What is the meaning of this?!
跟百夫长说我们一直都是从这条街过的
Tell the centurion we always process through the streets!
人民期望如此!
The people expect it!
我是希律王 他们必须让我通行
I am the King. They must let us through.
百夫长 这是怎么了?
Centurion, what is this?
禁止通行 这是上头的命令
No one passes. Those are our orders.
必须让希律王通行
The King must be allowed through.
他们让我们过去吗?
Are they letting us through?
- 让希律王过去!  - 管他是谁!
- Let the King pass!  - I don't care!
谁也不行!
No one!
不让
No.
该亚法 告诉我
Caiaphas, tell me,
为什么这座城好像要爆发了似的?
why does the city feel like it's about to erupt?
人民神经紧张 仅此而已
Nerves are jangling. Nothing more.
这和拿撒勒人
It couldn't have anything to do
被处决没有关系 对吧?
with the execution of the Nazarene, could it?
他死了 他的门徒被驱散了
He's gone, and his followers are dispersed.
那为什么街上挤满了罗马士兵?
Then why are the streets crammed with Roman soldiers?
巡抚... 情绪不定
The Governor's... unsettled.
哦 巡抚情绪不定 是吗?
Oh, the Governor's unsettled, is he?
难道不是因为你对整件事处理不当?!
It couldn't be that you mishandled the whole thing?!
你在夜里秘密审判了那个人
You tried the man at night, in secret,
违反了犹太律法
contrary to Jewish law,
然后你又让罗马人处决了他!
and then you had the Romans execute him!
我只是做了该做之事
I did what was necessary.
你这么做反倒让他变得重要起来了
You made him far more important than he need be.
我们老这么利用罗马人
Our continued use of the Romans
会让街上的民众
could be seen as collaboration
认为我们和罗马人勾结
by the average man in the street.
你现在倒理解街上的普通民众了 是吗?
You understand the average man in the street now, do you?
人并不需要变得普通
One doesn't need to be average
才能理解普通人 该亚法
to understand the average man, Caiaphas.
成千上万的朝圣者
With thousands of pilgrims
会在五旬节涌入街头
flocking into the street for Pentecost,
我们一定不能被视作与罗马关系太过紧密
we must not be seen to be too closely aligned with Rome.
要确保不会 该亚法
Ensure we are not, Caiaphas.
我们还能待在比这更差的地方吗
We couldn't have chosen a worse place to be.
- 这里很危险  - 简直是自杀
- It's dangerous.  - It's suicidal.
彼得
Peter.
马太! 哦!
Matthew! Oh!
- 大家都在吗?  - 基本都在
- Are we all here?  - Nearly.
我希望你是带着计划来的
I hope you come with a plan.
只有他给我们的那个...
Only the one he gave us...
回到耶路撒冷 然后等待圣灵的降临
To return to Jerusalem and wait for the holy spirit.
等多久?
For how long?
我和你知道的一样多 西门
I know as much as you, Simon.
他说要建造起他的教堂 怎么造? 用什么?
He said he'd build his church. How? With what?
我不知道
I don't know.
他会用这间房里缺少的
He'll build it with two things
两样东西来建造
that are lacking in this room...
信念...
belief...
和忍耐
and patience.
看我找到了谁
Look who I found.
玛雅
Maya.
那么我们就对所需何事达成一致了?
Then we are agreed on what is necessary?
是的 需要一个平安无事的五旬节
Yes. An uneventful Pentecost.
所以我们互相理解了
So we understand one another.
我的地位是不会动摇的
My position is unassailable.
然而 你的地位
Yours, however,
则仰赖于犹太公会的忠诚
is reliant on the loyalty of the Sanhedrin
和另一件事...
and one other thing...
我的认可
my endorsement.
再有处理不当
Any more mishandling
我们就必须认真重新考虑你的职位了
and we shall have to seriously reconsider your role.
给可怜的瘸子赏点东西吧?
Anything for a poor cripple?
给可怜的瘸子赏几个硬币吧?
A few coins for a poor cripple?
给可怜的倒霉蛋赏点东西吧?
Anything for a poor misfortunate?
给他一点钱 该亚法
Give him some money, Caiaphas.
愿神保佑你!
God bless you!
你买一个吗? 你从我这买一个吧?
You buy one? You buy one from me?
一边待着
Wait.
我是来帮你的
I am here to help.
愿神保佑你
God bless you.
在神殿这件事上
My husband's hands are tied,
我的丈夫有所掣肘
as far as the temple is concerned.
然而 与他们的建议相反
However, contrary to their suggestion,
我们愿意达成一项私人约定
we would like to come to a private arrangement
每年给你们一笔抚恤金
and give you an annual income,
至少到你的孩子长大成人
at least until your children are old enough
可以养活自己为止
to earn for themselves.
为什么神殿不想救助我们?
Why would the temple not want to help?
我的丈夫是一个深受尊敬的祭司
My husband was a well-respected priest.
信得过他 才派他去看守那个拿撒勒人的坟墓
He was trusted to guard the Nazarene's tomb.
确实如此...
He was...
那究竟有什么事?
What is it?
没什么
Nothing.
- 你究竟有什么事不告诉我?  - 我该走了
- What aren't you telling me?  - I should go.
为什么神殿不批准赡养他的家人?
Why would the temple not endorse support for his family?
他是不是做错了什么事?
Had he done something wrong?
求你了 告诉我
Please, tell me.
我要知道他为什么被人杀害
I need to know why he was murdered.
你必须马上离开耶路撒冷...
You must leave Jerusalem immediately...
而且永远不再回来 免得遭受同样的命运
and never return without suffering the same fate.
我们会每年给你抚恤金
As well as the annual income,
还会给你找一个新家
we will find you a new home.
在离这够远的地方
Somewhere far away enough
这样你 尤其是你的孩子
so that you and, more importantly, your children
才能够重新开始
can start again.
我上回来这里的时候 有个来自安纳托利亚的乐师
When I was here last, you had musicians from Anatolia.
从基利家来的 是的
From Cilicia, yes.
基利家 没错
Cilicia, yes.
这就是生活在罗马管辖下的
Yet another example of the advantages
好处之一
of living under Rome's influence.
还有得到改善的港口 贸易路线
Along with the improved ports, trading routes,
船运 法律 音乐 诗歌
shipping, laws, music, poetry.
我们更愿意称其为你来我往的
We like to think that our cultural interaction
文化交流
goes both ways.
我们目前在庆祝的
This festival of Pentecost,
这个五旬节
which we are currently celebrating,
是为了纪念我们与摩西律法自古以来的联系
commemorates our link back to the laws of Moses,
然而也加强了我们在当今世界里的作用
and yet enhances our role in the modern world.
归功于罗马帝国的宽容 你们才得以自由发挥
A role that, thanks to Roman tolerance,
你们的作用
you're free to express.
一定程度上是这样
To a degree.
我是神殿的管理者兼守护者
I am warden and guardian of the temple,
因此 我想我要提出一个小要求
and as such, I feel I have a small request to make.
你说
Go on.
在这个时期 让罗马士兵围住神殿
Roman soldiers around the temple this time of year
可无益于让人民感受到您的宽容
do not help to make the people feel your tolerance.
实际上恰恰相反
Quite the opposite, in fact.
我们都心知肚明我们的国土被罗马占领了
We are all too aware that we are an occupied country.
那你有何建议?
And what do you suggest?
我建议您从我的神殿撤军
I would suggest that you remove your troops from my temple
让我的人民能和平欢度他们的节日
and let my people celebrate their festival in peace.
你的人民 你的神殿?
Your people and your temple?
我知道您无意让局面动荡不安
I understand your intentions are not to incite unrest.
不 不 不
No, no, no.
这可不是你的城市
It's not your city.
我来告诉你我会做什么吧
I'll tell you what I'll do.
我会在神殿周围部署双倍巡逻
I'll double my patrols around the temple,
我还会亲自去参加这个节日
and I'll attend the festival myself, in person.
宴会结束了 哥尼流
The party's over. Cornelius.
我敦请您劝劝他
I urge you to counsel him.
从来没有巡抚参加过这个节日庆典
No governor has ever attended a festival.
太有挑衅意味了
It will be highly provocative.
无论我的丈夫做任何事 我都支持他
I support my husband in all he does.
你一个人来这的?
You traveled here alone?
在河边看见你后没多久 我就出发了
I set off soon after I saw you by the river.
我知道我们必须再次离开
I knew we had to leave again.
我不想伤害你
I didn't want to hurt you.
但你还是伤害了
And then you did.
我跟祖母说了要带你回家
I told grandmother I'd bring you home.
她想你
She misses you.
我还不能回家
I can't come home yet.
那我就等到你能为止
Then I'll wait until you can.
- 你不能留在这 玛雅  - 为什么不行?
- You can't stay here, Maya.  - Why not?
要不了多久 我们又要搬走了
We're moving again, ourselves, soon.
我不介意
I don't mind.
我们在这做的事情... 会很危险
What we're doing here... It could be dangerous.
追随拉比有什么危险的?
What's so dangerous about following a rabbi?
你还戴着它啊
You're still wearing it.
真坚强
Iron.
跟我讲讲家乡的事儿
Tell me a story from home.
艾弗纳的儿子 约书亚
Avner's son, Joshua,
他觉得他已经是个特别厉害的捕鱼人了
thinks he's a great fisherman now,
但他其实才乘船出海了三次
but he's only been out in the boat three times.
在神殿山上会部署300士兵
You'll have 300 men on the temple mount,
还有500守卫同您一起
and you'll be accompanied by 500 bodyguards.
我们尽可能速进速出
We go in fast and get out as quickly as we can.
不行
No.
要是我置身500人中间 民众还怎么能看见我?
If I'm in the middle of 500 men, how can I be seen?
你和50名士兵同我一起 不能再多了
You and 50 men shall accompany me, no more.
遵命
As you wish.
我希望这可不仅仅是个"让别人看见我"的问题
I hope this is more than just a case of "look at me."
我早就该这么做了...
I should have done this ages ago...
让他们看看谁才是真正掌权的人
Show them who's really in charge.
你应该听百夫长的话
You should listen to your centurion.
我应该做的是带你去床上
What I should do is take you to bed.
明天之前你都该好好休息
You need to rest before tomorrow.
我们不能出去吗?
Can't we go out?
一旦街上的士兵少点了... 我们就出去
We'll leave... once there are less soldiers on the streets.
只要我们最近不到外面去
If we don't get back out there soon,
- 大家都会把我们给忘光了  - 不 他们不会的
- everyone will have forgotten who we are.  - No, they won't.
你真以为我们吓到了那些当权者?
Do you really think we scared the authorities?
他们要是知道那件事会吓得更厉害
We'd scare them even more if they knew.
知道什么事?
Knew what?
知道我们已经看见了他
That we'd seen him.
多马
Thomas.
看见了谁?
Seen who?
耶稣
Jesus.
我们每个人还同他说话了
We've spoken to him, all of us.
你不会相信的 对吗?
You don't believe this, do you?
开始的时候我吓坏了
I was scared at first.
我想我们都吓坏了
I think we all were.
但他有血有肉 像你一样真实
But he was as real as you are now.
那你们为什么不出去告诉大家呢?
Then why aren't you out there telling people?
为什么你们要把自己关在这里?
Why are you all shut away up here?
我们在等待
We're waiting.
等待什么?!
For what?!
圣灵降临
The holy spirit.
那又有什么用?
How will that help?
当它降临... 我们自会知道
We'll... know when it gets here.
那它什么时候降临?
And when does it get here?
这你也不知道?
You don't know that, either?
你问得太多了!
So many questions!
是你教我要提问的 记得吗?
You taught me to ask questions, remember?
她可真是你女儿
She's definitely your daughter.
朋友...
Friend...
有什么消息吗?
you have information?
是的
Yes.
哥尼流召回了所有的百夫长
Cornelius has recalled all centurions,
我还听说彼拉多会在五旬节造访神庙
and I hear Pilate will visit the temple on Pentecost.
这是对我们圣地的亵渎
This desecration of our sacred space
这就是先知们所说的可憎之事
is the abomination the prophets talked about.
那我们下手的时间就到了
Then our time has come to kill him.
每当这样的夜晚 我都希望我回到了凯撒利亚
It's nights like this I wish I was back in Caesarea.
我在这里无法入睡
I cannot sleep here.
这里过去是我父亲的宫殿
This used to be my father's palace.
在我们之前是
Before us.
在你们之前是
Before you.
我要回去睡了
I was going back to bed.
祝你睡得安稳
I wish you a restful night.
你也是
You too.
你为什么还没睡?
What's keeping you awake?
我猜 是跟你一样的原因
The same thing as you, I'd imagine.
关于明天
Concern about tomorrow,
彼拉多的安全一事
for the safety of Pilate.
向我保证你会保护好他
Promise me you'll take care of him.
这是我职责所在
That's my job.
那就好好干
Do it well.
你们还记得在加利利的时候 这个人 他抓住了...
Do you remember in Galilee, this man here, he caught...
没人见过 没有人见到过
No one ever saw it. No one ever saw it.
那是我见过最大的鳟鱼...
This was the biggest trout...
如果他们找到你...
If they find you...
他们会杀掉你吗?
will they kill you?
不会
No.
他们可杀了他
They killed him.
所以呢?
So?
他们会吗?
Will they?
我不知道
I don't know.
彼拉多明天打算亲自造访神庙
Pilate intends to visit the temple himself tomorrow.
那必须有人劝劝他
Well, he has to be dissuaded.
- 他为什么要去?  - 为了证明一件事
- Why is he coming?  - To prove a point.
向你?
To you?
向我们所有人
To all of us.
民众会受不了的
Well, the people won't stand for it.
我们比罗马人多
We outnumber the Romans.
我们可以关上神殿的门
We could always bar the doors.
这可是五旬节 我们的人也会被关在外面
At Pentecost, to our people, as well?
会引起骚乱的
It would be mayhem.
该亚法 你一定要有所行动
You must do something, Caiaphas.
也许 我们可以把他当作荣誉嘉宾
Perhaps we should receive him as our honored guest.
决不能让彼拉多把我们的节日变成血腥屠杀
Pilate cannot be allowed to turn our festival into a bloodbath.
你该睡觉了
You should be sleeping.
你也是
So should you.
你害怕吗?
Are you afraid?
是的
I am.
不是害怕罗马人或是祭司
Not of the Romans or the priests.
我怕自己并不是耶稣
I'm afraid I may not be the person
所想象的那个人
that Jesus thinks I am.
你在家的时候我总是有安全感
I always felt safe when you were home,
你很明确地知道自己想要什么东西
like you knew exactly what you wanted
以及怎样才能得到那件东西
and how you were going to get it.
那个时候 我只想多捕些鱼
Back then, all I wanted was fish.
有鱼就有钱赚
Fish meant money,
有钱就能买到食物和衣服
and money meant food and clothes.
那时的生活很简单
Life was simple.
现在不简单了吗?
And now it isn't?
如果他在这的话会怎么做?
What would he do if he were here?
他会祈祷
He'd pray.
约翰 起来了!
John, wake up!
大家...
All of you...
起来啊! 来啊!
Wake! Come!
我们要做什么?
What are we doing?
我们要祈祷
We're praying.
五旬节
我们在天上的父 愿人都尊你的名为圣
Our father in heaven, hallowed be your name.
愿你的国降临 愿你的旨意
Your kingdom come, your will be done,
行在地上 如同行在天上
on earth as it is in heaven.
我们日用的饮食 今日赐给我们 免我们的债
Give us today our daily bread, and forgive us our debts,
如同我们免了人的债
as we have also forgiven our debtors.
不叫我们遇见试探
And lead us not into temptation,
救我们脱离那恶者
but deliver us from the evil one.
我们在天上的父 愿人都尊你的名为圣
Our father who art in heaven, hallowed be your name.
愿你的国降临 愿你的旨意行在地上...
Your kingdom come, your will be done, on earth...
我们日用的饮食 今日赐给我们 免我们的债
Give us today our daily bread, and forgive us our debts,
如同我们免了人的债
as we have also forgiven our debtors.
不叫我们遇见试探
And lead us not into temptation,
救我们脱离那恶者
but deliver us from the evil one.
我们在天上的父 愿人都尊你的名为圣
Our father in heaven, hallowed be your name.
愿你的国降临 愿你的旨意
Your kingdom come, your will be done,
行在地上如同行在天上
on earth as it is in heaven.
我们日用的饮食 今日赐给我们 免我们的债...
Give us today our daily bread, and forgive us our debts...
现在我们要离开此地
Now we can leave this place.
现在我们为他传道
Now we spread his word.
不论如何 我们都要保护巡抚!
At all times, we shield the governor!
谁若敢上前一步...
The first person to step forward...
我就取他的首级
I'll have his head.
巡抚 大祭司要您跟着我
Governor, the high priest would ask that you follow me
从神殿的南门进去
and enter the temple through one of the south gates.
为什么?
Why?
那扇美门通往妇人院
The Beautiful Gate leads to the Court of the Women,
只有犹太人才能进入
which is for Jews only.
他还礼貌地要求您把武器留在外面
He also requests politely that you leave your weapons outside.
那我礼貌地拒绝这两条要求
I decline both requests politely.
我们就从这里进去
We enter here.
列队!
Cohort!
我们去哪?
Where are we going?
神殿啊 还能去哪?
The temple. Where else?
我希望你清楚自己在做什么 该亚法
I do hope you know what you're doing, Caiaphas.
你真的以为这样能行?
And you really believe this will work?
如果不成功 他们会同罗马人一起撕了我们
If it doesn't, they'll tear us apart along with the Romans.
请肃静!
Quiet, please!
肃静
Quiet.
请大家肃静
我知道以前从未有巡抚光临
但你们要明白
他来此是为赎自己的罪
他在说什么?
What's he saying?
他带了礼物向我们的信仰致敬
并要在神前屈身敬拜
所以与其谴责
我们应当宽容他
右边有情况!
Trouble to the right!
上!
Go!
别挡着路!
Get out of the way!
闪开!
Move!
哥尼流!
Cornelius!
让路!
Make way!
别挡着路!
Get out of my way!
起来
Up.
但愿你死得其所
I hope your cause is worth dying for.
愿你如此
I hope yours is.
给点钱吧 大人?
A few coins, master?
你看我们
Look at us.
我们没钱
We have no money.
金银我都没有
No silver, no gold.
只把我所有的给你 我奉拿撒勒人耶稣的名给你
But what I have I give you in the name of Jesus of Nazareth.
叫你起来行走
Rise up and walk.
藉着耶稣 这人能重新行走了
It's through Jesus that this man walks again.
神给我们差来他的仆人 耶稣
God sent us his servant, Jesus,
神又叫他从死里复活了
and God raised him again from death.
我们是他的见证
We are his witnesses,
圣灵与我们同在 让我们坚强
and the holy spirit is with us and makes us strong.
耶稣还活着
Jesus is alive.
让以色列众人知道...
Let all Israel know...
神立耶稣为主 为弥赛亚了
God made Jesus Lord and Messiah.
我以为你已经摆平这些信众了 该亚法
I thought you had dealt with these followers, Caiaphas.
加入我们
Join us,
你们也必领受圣灵
and you, too, will receive the holy spirit.
让他们闭嘴 以免再起骚乱
Silence them now, before he starts another riot.
来吧 拯救你们自己脱离这残酷的...
Come, save yourselves from this cruel wo...
彼得!
Peter!
耶稣已复活
Jesus is risen,
上帝将在天空显出奇事
and God will perform wonders in the sky above
在地上显出神迹!
and miracles in the earth below!
日头要变为黑暗 月亮要变为血!
The sun will turn to darkness and the moon to blood!
有人发现马尔库斯·德鲁苏斯被杀害了
Marcus Drusus was found murdered.
我们在附近逮捕了一伙人
We've arrested a group of men in the immediate area.
处决他们
Execute them.
我们认为凶手不在其中
W... we don't think the killer's among them.
在神殿台阶上处决他们所有人
Execute them all on the steps of the temple.
遵命
As you wish.
彼得
Peter.
- 玛利亚  - 约翰
- Mary.  - John.
其他人都很安全
All the others are safe.
你的伤...
Your wounds...
没什么
They're nothing.
外面的情况怎么样了?
What's happening out there?
他的道如燎原之火 就像圣灵一般
Word has spread like a fire, like the spirit itself.
许多许多人在奔我们而来 或许有数千人之多
Many, many people are coming to us, perhaps thousands.
玛雅
Maya.
她说在你安全回去之前是不会睡的
She says she won't sleep until you're safely back.
玛利亚 请你照顾好她
Mary, please take care of her.
我们可能永远出不去了
We may never leave here.
站起来... 快点
On your feet... Come on.
不! 不 不! 我是无辜的!
No! No, no! I'm innocent!
把杀手交出来
Deliver the assassin to us,
否则眼前这幕将不断重复上演
or this will become an all-too-familiar spectacle.
他们会找你的
They are going to be looking for you.
他们正在外邦人院处死嫌疑人
They're executing suspects at the Court of the Gentiles.
世态如此
It's the way of the world.
血债要血偿
Blood will have blood.
他荣光之国的名字 是应当称颂的
Blessed be the name of his glorious kingdom
直到永永远远
forever and ever.
以色列 你要听 主是我们的神
Hear, Israel, the Lord is our God.
是独一的主
The Lord is one.
他荣光之国的名字 是应当称颂的
Blessed be the name of his glorious kingdom
直到永永远远
forever and ever.
以色列 你要听 主是我们的神
Hear, Israel, the Lord is our God.
是独一的主
The Lord is one.
他荣光之国的名字 是应当称颂的
Blessed be the name of his glorious kingdom
直到永永远远
forever and ever.
我们的人已经不计其数了
We are already beyond counting.
当他们的信仰席卷整个大地 帝国开始施行报复
As their faith sweeps the land and the Empire retaliates.
杀手是冲我而来
The assassin came for me.
每天钉死十个犹太人...
Ten Jews will be crucified every day...
你知道这也不会容易
You knew this wasn't going to be easy.
绝不手下留情
There will be no mercy.
我儿子选择你是有原因的
My son chose you for a reason.